foreign
[Music]
a
get the booze going
I posted on Instagram and on YouTube
saying that we were going to do a q a
and I got Hoards of questions a lot
mostly about ice cream thankfully
obviously there are some very personal
ones that people decided to ask which
I'm not surprised about
I am gonna sit here Annie a bounty
chocolate bar because we've just
recorded the coconut conundrum
video which I don't know when it will
come out so if it's out already I'll put
a link below if it's not then ignore
that and you never heard me say it
so
let's get on to some of these questions
we're gonna do some personal ones first
get those out the way
how old are you I am 43
nice and easy I would be 44 on December
13th
why is my beard Gray
my beard is gray because I'm getting old
I actually went gray quite young but
some parts are holding on for dear life
much like my hairline but hey we can't
all be perfect
uh where do you live my family and I
live near Newbury which is in Berkshire
so we used to live near the queen now we
live near the king
we don't at all box is huge
um
on to some more food related things
rather than get rid of all those
personal kind of questions
will you ever make other desserts on the
channel
yes we did make some ice cream
sandwiches the cookies were kind of
styled like
uh cupcake Gemma cookies a New York
style cookies they were really good
cookies actually they were
I'll put a link below because they were
good cookies
and we were able to freeze them and cook
them later down the line but yes we're
gonna do some other kind of videos we've
got some planned for later this year I
think we're doing a couple aren't we but
it's just about expanding we'll always
be an ice cream Channel Wherever we
shake it but we are going to add in some
other kind of goodies as well things
like how we make the brownies that go in
our recipes the add-ins you know you've
got like cheesecake ice creams as well
so we'll we'll do videos on how we make
the cheesecake and stuff like that so
yeah we will expand a little bit
and you made a stonking cake for
obviously devoted to Moon oh the
chocolate blackout cake Brooklyn
blackout cake that's what it's called
hold on
hopelessly devoted to Moon
that was under the old channel name
yeah Brooklyn blackout K that was really
good actually we just recently watched
Jamie from anti-chef make his version of
Brooklyn blackout cake and I'm glad to
say that mine was equally as bad as his
so overall enjoyable very tasty though
next question
why don't you make no Churn ice cream
how long you got
no Churn ice cream
a it's not ice cream
it's a frozen dessert
I get why people make it
if you don't have an ice cream machine
or you don't have freezer space for one
of the containers of from an ice cream
machine
you don't have the money for an ice
cream machine or you just don't make
enough of it to even warrant buying one
then I get it
but there are some distinct problems
with no child ice cream that nobody ever
talks about and that is it's very high
fat content usually in the early to mid
20 percent
fat range sugar wise usually the same
so actually what you're making is
something that is incredibly bad for you
I mean ice cream already is pretty bad
for you
but it's really bad for you
will I do no churn in the future Maybe
but I enjoy it
no
but it's not all about doing what you
enjoy I know some people or I should say
a lot of people have asked me to do some
no chain recipes
so the likelihood is in 2023 I will do
some
um
yeah that's it
next question
why do you spell flavor wrong on most
videos
that came from an American I don't
I'm English so over here you know expect
to see that kind of spelling for flavor
and color and we don't use cups over
here I'm not doing cups it's uh
it's a 2022 measuring things with it you
might as well go up and use a shovel and
a bucket to measure things out come on
buy some scales
next question
my wife's laughing the background
next question do you eat all the ice
cream you make on the channel
do I eat all of it no
I eat a lot of it
we try and limit ourselves
as a family to ice cream certain days of
the week because as you can imagine the
amount of ice cream that I make
not just on here but in general it's way
too much to consume so I give it away to
various people the the ice cream that we
make on the channel so it might be my
mum my mother-in-law
friends they they just literally take
what they like
but
that kind of leads on to another
question is how much ice cream do you
eat
a lot
weekly I don't know
a liter maybe depending on how good the
week's going maybe a little bit more
maybe one and a half liters it's
probably more of a question how much do
we drink
but that's a different video altogether
it's not a lot
uh next question can I get a video of
the tubs being drawn we have tried
we have tried doing that but it's
it doesn't really work out because
having a toddler you're always doing a
little bit here and a little bit there
you're doing it when she's asleep or
playing on her own or at Nursery
whatever you we don't often have on my
wife because I don't do them
we don't have the time that enables her
to sit down set up a camera and and film
it plus the tub is always being moved
around to suit so it's very difficult to
capture all on camera so
as much as we would like to the
likelihood is no we're not going to be
able to make a video like that we'll try
and capture some little Snippets maybe
but we don't do as many of the drawn
tubs as we used to it's just very time
consuming and you know life takes over
next question
do you prefer ice cream or gelato
actually
I tell you ice cream
because it's I I prefer
fatty or I should say American ice cream
gelato just means ice cream
um American style actually because I
prefer the fattier recipes
but
you also can't beat that slight
chewiness of gelato you and a gelato
enables much stronger flavors to come
through due to lower fat percentage and
that actually does tie into another
question but I'll talk about that then
but if someone gave me gelato or ice
cream I'm never gonna turn it away
unless it's bad of course but yeah do I
have a favorite no I'll take whatever
comes my way
next question what is your favorite ice
cream of all time
oh I don't know it does change but if
we're looking at store-bought ice creams
I mean I kind of have to revert back to
Ben and Joe's and Häagen-Dazs
fish food
and Haagen-Dazs building chocolate
those are probably my favorite
yeah I'd say those are those two my my
favorite if I would if I were to go out
with nothing no means to make ice cream
those two flavors I'd buy more often
anything else
oh chocolate milk cookies
you can't buy that anymore
so
it's kind of a moot point but that was
one of my favorite flavors
we did
make that
howl
let's have three names over the years
uh chocolate Midnight Cookies midnight
fudge hello whatever the three names
I'll put them up on the screen I forget
but that that is a really good ice cream
and I remember having it as a teenager
so that might sneak into a third
maybe joint second don't confuse me next
question
what are the costs of making your own
ice cream obviously that depends on what
one you make if you just make vanilla
and you use vanilla extract the cost
would be very low things like lemon or
orange we've just finished the recording
the orange rectification video
that's very cheap you know citrus fruit
you can buy a Whole Net five six seven
of each fruit for not a lot of money
um
is going to change depending on where
you're making it Dairy costs a lot of
money in some parts of the world and
costs nothing in others in England milk
is relatively cheap cream is going up in
price but still relatively cheap
the sugar
um you know five kilos of sugar over
here in a standard Supermarket not at
wholesale prices is two pound two pound
twenty it's not a lot of money so really
if you're making recipes of two liters
plus you can bring the cost of a 500 mL
tub one of these down to
in the one pound 21 pound 30 range
really cheap really really cheap
plus you can make it I hope you want it
if you're going to start making brownies
and cakes and
cookie dough and all that kind of stuff
then obviously that's going to increase
the price
exponentially
if you're going to make Stark Raven
hazelnuts I'll put a link to that below
get your wallet out because that was
really really pricey I think the the
biggest expense for that one was the
bottle of alcohol which Laphroaig not
for me
um but you wouldn't use the whole bottle
for making it unless you've had a huge
great batch of it
um
so if you were to break the cost of that
down it was still expensive I think
when I worked at a cost of alcohol use
it was somewhere around eight pound a
tub so pretty pricey altogether
next question
how do I calculate extra sugars in
flavored milk now
depending on where you're going to get
your flavored milk
and how you're going to do it if you go
to a store and you buy flavored milk
that's actually really easy to calculate
because it states on the back in most
countries now legally it has to state
how much sugar
carbs fats protein
and salt is in
a recipe in a product
so if you were to buy let's say
chocolate milk off the shelf
you can look on the back and see that
per 100 milliliters or grams depending
on where you live you will have that
much sugar in it obviously if you're
using 300 milliliters rather than just
milk then you add up the sugar used
you add up the sugar that's in that milk
itself and subtract it from the overall
recipes amount that you're using so
let's say your recipe is I'm just going
to randomly pick numbers 500 mL or 500
grams worth of milk and you use 160
grams of sugar
if you're 500 grams of milk has 40 grams
of sugar in it then you would just
subtract the 40 grams of sugar that's in
your flavored milk from your overall
sugar content for the rest of the recipe
now
if you're gonna start steeping things
in your Dairy
like cereal
it's a much harder thing to do
there's no way to know how much sugar is
seeping out of that product into your
milk without testing it there's no way
to know and it would be different every
time
you can get tools to measure
sugar content I'll put a picture of one
up here
they're quite expensive you know and for
most home ice cream makers there's no
point a lot of people on Facebook groups
love to do it that's up to them you know
but most people wouldn't go out and buy
a tool specifically to measure the sugar
content of their ice cream they want to
make something that tastes good nice and
quick
in the machine away you go
so a couple of different options one you
can one you can't
next question
this is a long one
if I do not have a commercial stabilizer
what combination of other items such as
dextrose corn syrup by xanthan gums skim
milk powder Etc works well what items
would you consider make a significant
difference and what would be your
must-haves
stabilizers
people have got back or stabilizers got
a bad wrap over the years most of them
are actually come from seaweed so
they're vegan by and large and they're
just another off the shelf product but
they'll be given e-numbers
over in England and most of North
America so they've got this stigma
attached to them they're bad for you
they're absolutely not bad for you
um dextrose corn syrup
aren't stabilizers they're just types of
sugar
dextrose
is less sweet than sucrose but has a
higher effect on your freezing point
corn syrup
there's lots of different types of corn
syrup so corn syrup is an invert sugar
essentially but then you've got your
high fructose corn syrup your golden
syrup they're all invert sugars
um so they they're not stabilizers
xanthan gum is a stabilizer stabilizer
is quite a complex subject deserves much
more time than a minute or two just
rambling on about it but
if you were really just looking for the
least amount of product to stabilize
your ice cream
and you really want to get into it then
I would recommend locust bean gum and
guar gum those two combined will
stabilize your ice cream for quite a
period of time if you don't want to get
into stabilizers you can use skim milk
powder it will not stabilize it for as
long a period of time because what it is
doing is holding on to the free water in
your ice cream recipe
rather than those stabilizers that I
mentioned before the goigum and Locus
being gum they create gels Within
your ice cream base which will help
stabilize the mixture overall so they're
quite different approaches to
stabilizing ice cream
but if you want to know more about
stabilizers
let me know if I get enough people that
want to see it then I'll make an entire
episode on stabilizers and the types and
what they do
next question do you prefer ice cream
that is made with egg yolks versus
eggless your recipes are mostly eggless
so I guess that's the answer but what
factors made you switch
it's just much easier because I use
stabilizers
there's no point using eggs there's
there's really no point that modern
technology and food science has come on
such a way that you don't need to use
eggs
most people get confused as to why eggs
exist in ice cream recipes they think
that the whole Frozen Custard thing is
very different to ice cream
Frozen Custard
is a different product to American ice
cream and gelato so the texture is very
different and the result is very
different it's borderline Frozen pudding
if you will
eggs
scientifically you're just looking for
the less than in there too excuse me
to act as an emulsifier within the base
which makes the fats and Waters combine
into a more stable solution
you don't need to do that with
stabilizers you can buy proprietary
mixes off the shelf ice cream stabilizer
from special ingredients I'll put a
picture up here and that's got a mix of
lots of stabilizers and emulsifiers
already in it so you can just take
however much you need out of that sling
it in and once that's all heated up to
the same temperature the eggs would need
to be heated up to anyway to make sure
they're cooked you've created the same
texture as a custard base but without
all the fuss and hassle plus people have
got this weird
notion that you must temper eggs in the
same way that has been tempered for the
last 150 years
and
in a way I just get bored of telling
people that you don't need to do it
people still do it and you know over the
years I've seen people that need 16 egg
yolks in a five star five Michelin star
Vanilla Ice Cream
what are you doing why would you do that
you might as well just go out and murder
chickens but you know they're just
pointless
excuse me
next question
I could go on about the whole eggs and
ice cream ages
what do I need to consider when making a
fruit ice cream to ensure that it's
still scoopable not icy and not hard
such as Peach and pineapple Apple Etc
what should I consider regarding their
juice and how does that affect the ice
cream since it's mostly water I don't
want a mild flavor I want the fruit
flavor to shine through and slap me in
the face in their terms
um
interesting question
one I should drink upon
fruit flavors can be quite weak
with most fruits you need to cook them
down with sugar the sugar pulls the
water out of the fruits so
when people do strawberry
we did the vegan strawberry here so we
actually macerated that with the
strawberries with the sugar pulled the
moisture out of the strawberries allowed
us to then evaporate some of that water
off and create like a semi strawberry
jam if you will
do that with any kind of fruit you like
give or take a few
you can roast them in the oven you can
cut them up and put them in a pan with
the sugar those kind of things what
you're trying to do is you're trying to
create a much stronger version of that
fruit juice
and when you do that with the sugar
you're creating an invert sugar I
mentioned that in an orange video that
we've just finished filming
I don't know if it's out yet if it is
I'll put a link down below if it's not
I'll flash up a picture here so you can
see what it looks like but that was
helping someone out who came to us via
Kofi they sent a recipe saying I'm
really struggling with the ice with this
orange ice cream this is what I've got
so in that video we talk about
how to rectify this recipe and the first
one that you sent us had no flavor and
that's because it was Reliant purely on
the juice so orange lemon juice has a
very limited flavor profile it doesn't
stick around add that to dairy fat
essentially and you start to lose all
the flavor most of flavor in
citrus fruit comes from the essential
oils that's in the skin
so for those kind of fruits you would
take those essential oils and steep them
in your base for as long as you can
without the base going off you know
overnight is usually enough warm it just
slightly on the hob
um you know I'll just put a little video
up here of of the simple process of
doing it and what you get is a really
nice strong pungent flavor as for
pineapple I've never made pineapple ice
cream
I love pineapple but
I do get acid indigestion problems
pineapple is not good if you have acid
reflux
um apple is actually really difficult
it's
I've tried quite a few Apple ice creams
over the years and I went to a company
that sold gelato and tried Apple gelato
and it was shocking really really bad
um
we saw some in Japan where we went on a
honeymoon but I didn't actually eat it I
wish I had but I think I'm going to try
an apple ice cream just see how to get
that kind of flavor through but it's
going to be very similar process you
know we're gonna we're gonna cook those
apples down to get that flavor boosted
there's no essential oils in the actual
skin so I don't know we'll see we get on
our ice creams
I don't like banana ice cream
if you watch it or if you did watch that
video you'll you'll find out
why I
just not a fan bananas
but
the longer you leave bananas before
going moldy the stronger the sugar or
the carbs get converted into sugar
they're much easier to process in your
ice cream
but even just putting bananas in your
Dairy and leaving it
will Empower a really strong banana
flavor
by roasting the bananas like we did in
ours
it really helped to bring that banana
flavor through
and although I'm not a banana ice cream
fan it was really good ice cream
next question
can we make sugar nope
can we make ice cream that is sugar-free
and suitable for diabetic patients like
the Australian ice cream brand dinada
never had that never been to Australia
um
you can
it's much harder than people think there
are a few people out there that have
done it really well
um I had a quick look at their
ingredients
something was quite interesting made us
both laugh
don't eat too much of it because it's
relaxative and that's because the type
of sugar substitute that they use
um you know you've got things like
Xylitol
and if you eat too much of that at all
go through here
um but there is a sugar substitute that
is in North America that apparently is
very very good we don't have it
available here so I can't do anything
with it but
but yes I will do
sugar-free ice cream in 2023
um
it's not that difficult to be fair but
it's just finding the right combination
of sugar substitutes that's all it is
and that leads us to our final question
for our first q a
what is the best way to get a strong
flavor in ice cream whether it be
pistachio or almond paste or whatever
that is quite simple
drop the fat
gelato has a much easier way of bringing
flavors forward
dairy fat dolls flavors massively egg
has a flavor profile that allows it to
overtake other flavors as well so if you
want
a strong flavor ice cream go with no egg
gelato bases
and that's really the best way to do it
then it's about how to increase the
strength of that flavor by whatever it
is you're making if it's pistachio I do
it personally I don't know most
commercial sellers or pistachio ice
cream do it as well they add almond
extract
because the flavor profiles of
flavonoids are within almond extract
actually complement that of pistachios
some people hate adding almond extract
to pistachio and they want the flavors
of the pistachio to come through but
not all pistachios are equal
some are flavorless some are really
strong flavored
so unless you know what type you've got
then you don't really know how to treat
your ice cream base if you've got a
really nice strong flavored pistachios
you'll be all right with just that you
know you can toast them in the oven
Blitz up turn it into a pistachio butter
keep some pieces to add in after and go
that route if you don't have a flavor
left you if you don't have a flavorful
pistachio then you might want to add
almond extract like we did
yeah
tubs up there somewhere
the vegan pistachio was great ice cream
really really good
um I'll put a link below for that as
well if you want to see it
But ultimately it's it's knowing your
ingredients and how strong the flavor is
you know if if the orange that you're
using is not particularly flavorful it's
because you've used the wrong part of
the orange to flavor your ice cream if
the chocolate that you're using isn't
imparting much flavor it's because
you're using a low-fat cocoa powder
likely non-dutched that will make it
very weak in flavor
um things like coffee instant coffee in
North America is
um we had a look when we were there and
I just couldn't drink it it's disgusting
so I threw it in a bin over in England
instant coffee is really good really
really good
um I'm quite happy using that for coffee
ice cream because you can get a really
strong really good coffee flavor without
going a whole bean root
but this is what's available to you you
know a lot of people don't like the fact
that I use instant coffee in coffee ice
cream
not surprised when their instant coffee
tastes like dirt scraped off the street
um
if they were to come over here and try
the instant coffee that we have
available I mean it's not all good some
of it's crap over here but some of it is
really really good and you know I'm a
coffee lover I drink a lot of it so
it's it's knowing what other people use
in relation to what you're expecting
so for coffee for instance if you're
expecting to use beans
and you come here and you see me use
instant you'll likely get pissed off
But ultimately if you don't live in the
country and you don't know what this
coffee is like
you don't know it's very good coffee I
wouldn't use Bad Coffee in the ice cream
but if you also know that you like
coffee beans and that's what you drink
use that
makes no difference you used ingredients
that you like make the ice cream that
you like
make it how you want to make it don't
listen to all the naysayers that are
floating around the internet say oh no
you must do this you must use 150 eggs
in your ice cream base to make a custard
that is as dense as Queen of sheba's ass
milk bath I don't know it doesn't make
any difference just literally make your
ice cream how you want to make it it
doesn't matter what other people think
you're the one eating it so
that's that's kind of why people are
you're right
that's why some people like to belittle
others on the internet
[Music]
I was talking about the queen yeshiva's
ass that's donkey not her ass a donkey
so there's a lot of
questions relating to ice cream
and you're never gonna get it perfect
because everyone likes to do things a
different way
so ultimately
the recipes that I put up for you you're
free to use however you want to use them
if you find that one of them has got too
much sugar drop the sugar to a to a
level that you're happy with
I like my ice cream scoopable stroke in
the freezer a lot of people aren't
bothered by that they'll take it out of
the freezer for 5-10 minutes let it warm
up slowly and then scoop it that way
whatever works for you it's all good
it's all gravy
as
as people in the 1800s used to say they
didn't
um anyway that's it
q a number one
done
we'll do another one next year
um we're almost a thousand subscribers
which is a big Landmark for us I've been
doing this Channel and coming up to two
years in January I think it is
um
so hopefully we can get to that thousand
subscriber Mark before the end of 2022
if you fancy supporting the channel you
can find us on Kofi it's a patreon
alternative I'll put a link below and
I'll put the details on the screen here
as well that just enables you to offer
support and make sure that we can keep
doing what we're doing here YouTube
monetization is quite limiting but
whilst we're almost at the subscriber
count for it we're nowhere near the view
time for it so if you're gonna wait for
that it's gonna be a while so anything
you can help with would be much
appreciated thanks very much for
watching don't forget to like And
subscribe and we'll see you next time
[Music]
thank you